LLMs are really good now. And AI coding
tools, also really good. But have AI
coding agents gotten any better at
aligning to the way that you and your
team want your products to be built? Not
really. You know the drill. You're
prompting your agent, always having to
over-explain how you want it to code
something. And sure, maybe it follows
your instructions this time, but what
about that next feature? And the one
after that? It forgets. It drifts. And
suddenly you're stuck in this loop where
you're re-explaining your coding
standards, fixing the same mistakes,
rewriting code that shouldn't have been
written that way in the first place.
This is why many developers and teams
get frustrated with AI coding agents.
And then they miss out on the benefits
and the potential that these tools can
bring. If only they could be trained in
the right way. And so earlier this year
I released the first version of Agent
OS. That's my free open-source system
for powering your spec-driven
development process with any AI coding
tool. And from day one, Agent OS was
designed to solve two fundamental
problems that professional developers
and teams face in AI-first development.
First, Agent OS gets your coding agents
aligned to your style, your patterns,
and your approach. In other words,
getting AI coding agents to code like
you code. And second, Agent OS creates
real consistency in your development
process. Spec-driven development has
proven to be the professional standard
when it comes to building large, complex
features in a systematic way. And Agent
OS helps you implement spec-driven
development with a proven system that
all coding agents can follow reliably.
And honestly, I've been blown away by
the response to the earliest versions of
Agent OS. Dell said that Agent OS
improved the output that I'm seeing from
Claude Code in a real way. It made my
workflow much more reliable. And this
comment from Manas, "Agent OS is the
most disciplined coding environment in
the agentic world. It adapts beautifully
to any tech stack and executes specs
effortlessly." Hector said, "This is
awesome. I've seen so many context
engineering setups and this is one of
the best that I've seen." I've also been
hearing from teams who are using Agent
OS as the foundation for AI adoption
across their organization. Because when
you give your team a shared system for
working with AI, then everyone can
actually benefit from shipping faster,
delivering higher-quality work, not just
the few engineers who had the time to
figure out this AI stuff on their own.
Justin said, "I can see how this system
is beneficial for AI agents, but it's
also extremely helpful for development
teams, especially new hires." Now over
the past few months, while thousands of
developers and teams have been using the
early versions of Agent OS, two major
developments happened. First, the tools
have been getting better and they're
evolving incredibly fast. Claude Code in
particular and its introduction of
sub-agents, that was a game-changer in
my view. But other tools like Cursor,
Codex, Gemini, they all keep shipping
incredible improvements to how we
interface with coding agents.
Second, I keep learning more about the
best practices and the patterns for
training and working with coding agents
in the way that they're actually
designed to be used. And so those
developments led me to completely
rethink the architecture under Agent OS.
They led to breakthroughs and major
improvements in how Agent OS delivers on
its original promise, helping your
coding agents better align to your way
of coding, and driving consistency in
your spec-driven development process.
And so today I'm thrilled to show you
Agent OS 2.0.
Now before I get into it, there are a
few things that you should know about
this project. First, if we haven't met
yet, I'm Brian Castle. I'm the creator
of Agent OS and I'm the founder of
Builder Methods. That's where I help
professional developers and teams stay
ahead of the curve when it comes to
building with AI. And every week I send
a free email called the Builder
Briefing. That's a 5-minute read to help
you stay sharp and up-to-date. And
subscribers get to hear about my live
workshops where we cover what's actually
working right now in AI-first
development. Now Agent OS is supported
and sustained through the Builder
Methods Pro membership and community,
along with my private engagements with
teams who are implementing Agent OS in
their organization. Now what that means
is this system is not backed by a
commercial AI coding tool or a major
tech platform. So it's unbiased, it's
tool agnostic, and it's tech stack
agnostic. My goal with Agent OS is to
provide an operating system that
enhances how you work with your coding
agents, no matter which AI coding tools
you use to interface with them. And
that's what's fascinating to me. Every
person and every team has their own
personal approach to how they build with
AI. So the workflow powered by Agent OS
is specifically designed to be modular.
Use all of its parts or only some of
them. And you can configure Agent OS to
fit your setup and your projects. For
example, if you're using Claude Code,
you can configure it to delegate to
sub-agents for context efficiency, or
you can stick with a single agent for
token efficiency. You can even set up
different profiles for coding standards
for the different types of projects that
you and your team work on. Now before we
start building features in our app, it's
important to establish what it is that
we're building here. Agent OS calls this
the plan product command. You would
typically run plan product only once at
the start of your project or on the day
that you've installed Agent OS into an
existing project. This creates your
product's mission, its road map, and its
tech stack. Three simple files in your
code base that serve as a reminder to
you, to your team, and to your coding
agents what it is that you're building,
who it's for and why, and a rough plan
as to which features you're going to
build in which order. Now from here on
out, your workflow will be a repeating
cycle that follows the three main phases
of the spec-driven development process.
Planning a feature and writing the spec,
creating a list of tasks to track your
build, and implementing the feature.
Agent OS breaks these into a series of
commands, so you can use all of them or
you can pick and choose the ones that
slot into your workflow. Let's start
with shape spec. This command will have
your agent guide you through the
strategic planning for a new feature.
Your agent will ask you a couple of
rounds of targeted questions, which are
easy for you to just confirm or course
correct to make sure that you're on the
same page about every detail.
You can also provide visuals like
mock-ups and wireframes and screenshots,
which your agent will use to dial in
your UI. You'll end up with a
requirements.md file, which contains all
those details that you've just hashed
out through this planning process. But
if you've already planned out your
feature with your own notes, your own
way, then you can simply drop those
right into requirements.md and move
right into the next phase. So now we're
ready to formalize our plan with a
written spec. Here you'll want to run
the write spec command. This instructs
your agent to write up a clear and
cohesive spec.md file based on the
information it's gathered and jotted
down in your requirements.md.
Your spec will include an overview, use
cases, what's in scope and out of scope,
and some technical notes for
implementation. Now once we're happy
with our spec, but before we start
coding anything, we'll run the create
tasks command, which gives us a clear,
trackable road map for implementation.
This lives in tasks.md, where tasks are
broken down, grouped up, and laid out in
a logical order for development. So
we've done that critical upfront
planning, we've written up our spec,
we've mapped out a clear list of tasks
for implementation. Now we're ready to
push forward with having our agents
start coding our feature with the full
confidence that they're going to get it
right and that they're going to build it
according to our standards. Now there
are two different commands to choose
from when it comes to implementing your
specs with Agent OS. You can run
implement tasks or orchestrate tasks.
What's the difference? Well, implement
tasks is simpler and it works great for
small-to-medium-sized builds where a
single agent will knock out your task
list. You can have it build out all your
task groups in one shot or you can take
it step by step. Orchestrate tasks is a
more advanced approach that lets you
orchestrate multiple agents to build out
a large or complex feature. If you're
using Claude Code, this gives you an
easy way to delegate task groups to
specialized sub-agents. Or if you're
using any other coding tool, orchestrate
tasks will generate targeted prompts
with your standards injected into them
for executing each set of tasks for this
feature. Now as you wrap up development
on a feature, Agent OS runs a
verification process, which includes
running and passing all the tests that
were written during development. Now I
find that by this point, typically all I
need to do is a bit of polish, maybe a
small fix or two, and my feature is
ready to deploy to production. So you
can go ahead and use Agent OS for free
by going to buildermethods.com/agentos.
That's where you'll find detailed
documentation on every aspect of the
system. For direct support and our
community of professional builders using
Agent OS, I invite you to join Builder
Methods Pro. Membership includes direct
support for Agent OS, training and
project resources, our private Discord
community, and access to my live
workshops. And if you're deploying Agent
OS with your team, I offer private
workshops and coaching on leveraging
Agent OS across your organization. And
don't forget to subscribe to the channel
for weekly content on building with AI.
Let's keep building.